well now that we've got a really good
appreciation for the pieces of the router the input ports the output ports and
the switching fabric we're going to dive down deep into the topics of packet
scheduling and buffer management and we've seen how important these are with the Internet's
best effort service model packet loss and packet delay have had a profound effect
on what has to happen the transport layers and the application layers so now
we're going to dive down deep into the topics of packet scheduling and buffer
management and we'll take a look at how those can be used to control
and also mitigate packet loss and packet delay well let's get started by first
taking a look at input port queuing remember that we saw earlier that input
port queuing can happen when the routers switching fabric is less than the combined
rates of its incoming links in this case more packets can arrive in a
unit time then the switching fabric can possibly move from the input side of
the fabric to the output side and so queuing can occur on the input
side a queuing phenomena that's unique to the input side of the switching fabric
is what's known as head of the line blocking or hol end of the
line blocking occurs when packets at different input ports want to go to the
same output port if only one pack at a
time can be transferred from an input to
a given output port and if there are K
packets that want to go to the same
output port then K minus 1 of those
packets are going to have to wait on the
input side of the switch and if packets
have to wait they can also block the
packets behind them in their input queue
from moving forward and this is what's
known as head of the line blocking take
a look at this example here where the
colors of the packets correspond to the
output port to which they're destined in
this example say at time T we see the
top and bottom input ports have a red
packet destined to the upper output port
in one clock deck the upper red packet
is transferred from the input to the
output side of the switch the blue
packet in the middle it's also able to
move from its input port to its output
port the red packet at the bottom
however is
locked from moving to the read output
port since the packet at the top was
already transferred there and so the
green packet behind this lower red
packet experiences head of the line
blocking let's now focus on the output
port side since this is really where the
action is and let's start by seeing why
buffering is needed in the first place
at this output port we have a link with
transmission rate of our bits per second
and let's say we have a non-blocking
switch capable of delivering end times
our bits per second to the output port
now we can see why buffering occurs bits
can be arriving at a rate of end times
are but bits can only be drained or
transmitted out at a rate of are
whenever the arrival rate exceeds the
departure rate the buffer will fill and
since buffers are finite there may not
be enough buffer space to store all of
the packets that need buffering and
packets will have to be dropped there
simply isn't enough memory to hold all
of the packets that need buffering so
right here at the output port is where
congestive packet loss occurs and you
know it may be tempting to say well it's
really the switch fabrics fault it's
delivering packets too fast at a rate of
end times are when the link can only
drain at rate R so we should slow the
fabric down but that's not really the
cause of the problem is it think back to
our earlier discussion of principles of
congestion control the real cause of the
problem congestion is that there are too
many transport layer senders at the edge
of the network sending too many packets
too fast packets whose paths cross at
this congested output port in the face
of buffering and congestion there are a
couple of decisions that'll need to be
made at the output port first if there's
not enough room for all arriving packets
a packet drop policy will be needed to
determine which packets are going to be
dropped and if there are multiple
packets in the buffer awaiting
transmission a packet scheduling
discipline will be needed to choose
which packets among the many cute
packets will be transmitted next we'll
look at both drop and scheduling
policies in just a second now there are
a lot of really important idea
that we just talked about here on this
slide so make sure you've got it all
it's really important well you might be
thinking given buffering is such a big
concern how much buffering should a
router have and more to the point you
might also be thinking well hey
shouldn't it be a good idea to invest in
a lot of buffering with a lot of
buffering there'd be less packet loss
since there'll be more buffers to
observe the burstiness and packet flows
having more buffering must be a good
thing right well it might surprise you
that even after 50 years the question of
how much buffering is the right amount
of buffering is still pretty much an
unresolved issue there are some
recommendations you could take a look at
RFC 3439 and find a rule of thumb that
says the amount of buffering should
equal a typical RTT say a couple hundred
milliseconds times the output link
capacity there's also been more a recent
theoretical research that assumes that
transport layer senders are generally
independent of each other and recommends
dividing the RFC 34:39 amount of
buffering by the square root of n where
n is the number of flows crossing the
link and that's a lot less buffering and
while you might have the sense that
large buffers will generally result in
less loss and you could be right
large buffers do have a downside large
buffers mean larger delays and larger RT
T's large delays are bad for gamers and
for interactive teleconferencing users
where tens of milliseconds really do
matter but maybe even more importantly
large RTT delays mean that TCP senders
will be slower to detect and therefore
react to congestion you might recall
that when we studied delay based
congestion control we encountered the
saying that we want to keep the
bottleneck link just full enough to keep
the link busy but no fuller but that was
from the perspective of the sending
hosts when we think about the amount of
buffering we really do want buffers to
absorb short term statistical
fluctuation in packet arrival rates and
to keep the link busy but not to have so
much buffering that congestion control
action times become slow and sluggish
well buffering sort of like salt and
cooking you've got to find the right
amount
just the right amount makes things
better but too much can really ruin
things well who would have thought that
buffering and queuing at an output port
could actually be so complicated and so
subtle and you may ask yourself why is
that and it's really because it's here
at an output port buffer that the global
behavior of potentially thousands of
active senders worldwide are converging
as their flows all pass through the
single output link we see the
convergence of global internet scale
behavior at this one location deeply
inside the internet that's pretty cool
well we're next going to move on to the
mechanisms for buffer management and
packet scheduling and will find it
useful to think of an output port
abstractly as a queue as shown here of
course we're all familiar with queuing
systems in our daily lives banks at
buses at bus stops at food stores at
metros and many other places think about
how many cubes you've been in today
packets arrive to the queue they wait
for service and they're eventually
selected for service receive service and
then leave the queue the link layer
functions as the server when a packets
bits are being transmitted over the
outgoing link that packets in service if
an arriving packet emerges from the
switching fabric to find there's no free
buffer space either that packets going
to be dropped and that's known as tail
drop or an already queued packet could
be removed from the buffer and dropped
to make room for this newly arriving
packet say according to some kind of
priority mechanism for example there
might be a policy to drop low priority
packets say carrying end-user TCP
traffic rather than high priority
packets say carrying Network management
in control packets for the ISP as we
also learned when we studied Network
assisted congestion control a buffered
packet may also be marked with a
congestion indication to signal that the
link is becoming congested we learned
earlier that for the
internet's explicit congestion
notification ecn mechanism to bits in
the IP header type of service field are
used for ecn marking will see these bits
in the IP datagram header in the next
section when we study ipv4 but it's here
at the output ports and where congestion
occurs that these bits are going to be
set we can now look at several packet
scheduling disciplines that are used in
practice under first come first serve
scheduling packets are transmitted
simply in the order in which they arrive
to the output port we're all familiar
with first-come first-serve queuing I'm
guessing it's what people do the most we
all join the back of the queue and
customers are served from the front of
the queue
same thing with packets
we're all familiar with priority queues
you get that with Airlines platinum
diamond gold silver or bronze class of
service they all sound pretty fancy and
great but you definitely rather be
platinum than bronze and I think we all
probably have an intuitive understanding
of how priority disciplines work having
been in the lower priority class of
service and seeing later arriving people
in higher priority classes getting
service before us under priority
scheduling packets arriving at the
output link are classified into priority
classes on arrival at the queue as shown
here where we have a high priority red
class of traffic and a lower priority
green class of traffic the priority
queueing discipline will transmit a
packet from the highest priority class
that has a non-empty queue that is has
packets waiting for transmission the
choice among packets in that same
priority class is typically done in a
first-come first-serve manner this
animation shows packets arriving from
the top entering service according to a
priority discipline and then leaving the
queue in this example packet one arrives
finds the queue empty and enters service
while packet one is in service packet
two and three arrived when packet one
finishes both packets two and three are
buffered but packet three is chosen for
transmission even though it arrived
after packet two since it has higher
priority than back at two and so on
well we've now learned about the
priority queuing mechanism but you may still be wondering what is it that defines
a priority class in the first place how is it determined what goes into
priority class 1 or priority class 2 for example and this is actually determined
by the network operator by the ISP the ISP may decide that well network
management traffic's really important it's the highest priority class voice-over-ip gets higher priority than
email and so on and you remember
than email and so on and you remember
that by looking at the transport layer port numbers one can determine what type
of traffic is being carried by that data
graph now traffic type is one way in
which priorities could be determined
another way might be on the basis of
source or even destination addresses so
here's another possible way to classify
traffic into priority classes imagine
that a company is willing to pay an
internet service provider to give its
packets better service packets are less
likely to be dropped its packets suffer
less delay as a result if it's a search
company its search results get to users
faster if it's voice over IP the voice
is more responsive if it's streaming
video there's less spinning meals well
we've got the scheduling mechanisms to
do that whether or not a company is able
to pay for that kind of better service
actually gets us into the topic of
what's known as network neutrality we're
going to cover that in just a second but
first let's wrap up by looking at a few
more scheduling disciplines so we've
seen first-come first-serve and priority
scheduling under round-robin scheduling
packets are assigned to classes as with
priority scheduling however rather than
there being a strict service priority
among classes a round-robin scheduler
alternates service among classes for
example a round-robin scheduler would
choose a packet from class 1 followed by
a packet from class 2 followed by a
packet from class 3 and so on and if
there's no packet of a given class the
scheduler moves on to the next class in
the schedule
a generalized form of round-robin
queuing that's been widely implemented
in routers and practice is known as
weighted fair queuing wfq light priority
and round-robin scheduling arriving
packets are classified and queued in the
appropriate per class waiting area we
see here red green and blue packets
waiting for their service a weighted
fair queuing scheduler schedules classes
in a round-robin like manner first
serving class 1 then serving class 2
then serving class 3 and then assuming
there are just three classes repeating
that service pattern weighted fair
queuing differs from round-robin  that each class can receive a
in that each class can receive a
different amount of service in any interval of time and here's how it works
ideally each class of packets I has a
weight W sub I let's assume that all of
the weights the sum of W J say sum up to
1 under weighted fair queuing during any
interval of time during which there are
class I packets to send class I will
then be guaranteed to receive a fraction
of service W sub I that means if the
link has a rate R then each class of
service will get a guaranteed minimum
amount of bandwidth W sub I times R and
so we can see how weighted fair queuing
allows some type of a bandwidth
guaranteed to be made on a per class
basis network neutrality is an area
where our technical interests in
computer networking intersect with
social political and economic
considerations well we've already seen
the mechanisms for sharing resources but
what about the social political and
economic considerations about how those
resources are shared let's take a look
network neutrality is about the laws and
policies that govern how an Internet
service provider can use the traffic
control mechanisms that we've just
learned about packet scheduling in
particular to control network traffic so
what are some of the questions that
network neutrality addresses well it's
about a number of different things it's
about free speech for example cannon
Espie refused to carry some types of
traffic for example certain types of
news or political opinion it's also
about encouraging innovation and about
encouraging competition for example must
an isp give all companies big and small
equal treatment of their traffic as you
probably know different countries have
been adopting different stances with
respect to these questions we're going
to take a look at what's happening in
the united states since this is well
documented and has all been playing out
pretty publicly our textbooks got some
interesting references about net
neutrality worldwide that you might want
to take a look at in 2015 the United
States Federal Communications Commission
order on protecting and promoting an
open Internet defined three clear bright
line rules associated with network
neutrality let's take a look at what
they are the first bright line rule is
no blocking and here's what it says it
says that an isp quote unquote shall not
block lawful content applications
services or non-harmful devices subject
to reasonable network management in
quote now there's a lot packed in there
the word lawful and applications
services and devices well this rules
about blocking traffic and there
actually was a case involving an ISP
that had a practice of blocking its
customers from using vonage which is a
voice over IP service that competed with
this is p's own telephone service that
would not be allowed and notice the
phrase subject to reasonable network
management will cover network management
when we cover the network layer control
plane but note here that it is allowable
to block traffic for network management
purposes say if the networks been
degraded and then only trickles of
traffic can get through then it's best
that network management traffic be able
to get through of course the question of
what reasonable network management is is
left open to interpretation
the second bright-line rule is no
throttling that is an isp quote unquote
shall not impair or degrade lawful
Internet
effect on the basis of Internet content
application or service or use of a non
harmful device again subject to
reasonable network management note here
the words impaired or degrade there was
a case not too long ago where an ISP was
judged to be interfering with BitTorrent
peer-to-peer traffic and it was doing
this by internally creating and sending
TCP reset packets to BitTorrent client
and servers executing at the end host
this caused the host to close their
BitTorrent connections basically the ISP
was closing the TCP connection
underneath the BitTorrent application
whose traffic it really didn't want and
then finally there's the bright-line
rule of no paid prioritization
this means for example that video
streaming traffic from all video streaming service providers must be treated the same for
example that one streaming video service provider cannot pay to get its packets better
service on their way to the customer and of course we've seen how this
can be done from a technical point of view via priority queuing well you
might ask why no paid prioritization since paying for a priority service seems well
almost like a fact of life at least here in the United States well
one of the arguments is that if say a video streaming service provider can
pay for better service and if that successful incumbent the existing service provider can
pay a lot then this introduces a high barrier to entry for new competitors
and of course some countries want to encourage market competition but there are counter
arguments to this claiming that creating additional revenues for an ISP by having paid
prioritization is a good thing from a competitive point of view since that makes
the ISP marketplace more lucrative and so more companies will want to invest in
the ISP market or ISPs will want to invest more in their infrastructure and
then finally there are laws going back almost a hundred years that have regulated
the telephone network as a telecommunications service provider but there's much less regulation of
information service providers so what is an ISP is it a telecommunication service provider
or an information service provider well it turns out from a regulatory standpoint the
answer to this question matters a lot in the US but the answer to
this question has really not yet been finally determined well these bright-line rules are
from a 2015 u.s. FCC order more recent FCC orders have actually rewritten much
of that 2015 order so until laws are written and until there's further litigation
and case law adopted I think it's fair to simply say that the situation
continues to evolve and I think that's true in many countries it's interesting that
we've had the ability to do prioritization since the internet first became public nearly
30 years ago so although the Internet has a strong technical foundation as we've
seen three decades later our social political and economic policies governing this creation that
have not yet been fully defined or agreed upon well that wraps up our
discussion of packet scheduling and packet buffering and also what I hope was an
interesting sidebar into the topic of network neutrality and more generally it wraps up
our discussion of what's inside a router remember we also looked at input ports
output ports and switching fabrics coming up next we're going to take a look
at the Internet Protocol ipv4 so stay tuned for that
you  [Music]